We have developed a simple but playable game.
我们开发了一个简单好玩的游戏
Now we need to find a way to break out
现在我们需要中断我们的
of our infinite loop spawning our waves
产生小行星的无尽循环
of hazards, end the game when the player is destroyed
当玩家被击毁的时候结束游戏
and give our players the chance to
允许玩家
restart a new game if they want to.
重新开始游戏
As we prepare to end the game
我们准备结束游戏
we need to create 2 new labels.
我们需要2个新标签
1 to display Game Over
一个显示游戏结束
and the other to indicate when it's
另一个告知
okay to restart the game.
什么时候游戏可以重新开始
In an effort to keep our Hierarchy organised
为了让我们的层级组织更有效
let's create an empty parent game object
让我们新建一个父对象
to hold our current Score Text
来保存我们现有的得分文本
and the 2 new labels we are about to create.
和2个新的将要建立的文本
Rename the game object DisplayText
将父类改名为DisplayText(显示文本)
and reset the game object's transform.
将这个对象的位移重置一下
Add Score Text to DisplayText
把Score Text拖拽到DisplayText上
making Score Text a child of DisplayText.
让其成为DisplayText的子节点
Next create a new GUI text game object.
然后再新建一个GUI text对象
Rename it Restart Text
(5.0以后的版本请选择UI -> Text代替GUI Text)
and change the text property to
重命名为Restart Text
Restart Text.
并更改文本属性为Restart Text
Change the transform position to
把位置组件改为
(1, 1) on the X and Y.
X和Y分别为(1, 1)
This should place the restart text
这样restart text文本应该
up in to the upper right corner.
就会出现在右上方
But we can't see it.
但是我们看不到它
By adjusting the transform's position
我们可以通过更改transform组件的
on the X axis we can drag Restart Text
position属性的X方向的值把Restart Text
back in to the game screen.
文本拖拽回游戏屏幕
But again using the transform component
但是再重新说一遍使用transform组件来
for adjusting this fine detail on the GUI
实现对文本位置的微调
text label is not ideal.
不是一个好注意
Let's leave the transform position X at 1.
让我们把X方向上的位移值保持为1
There are 2 adjustments that we can make
这里还有2个地方的设置
in the GUI text component to better display
可以让我们更好的显示
our Restart Text label.
我们的Restart Text标签
The first is our anchor and alignment.
第一处设置就是锚定和调整
Currently these are set at default
目前这些设置都是使用默认的
or upper left and left.
左上和左
This is why we cannot see our label.
这就是我们看不到我们文本标签的原因
The label is starting at the upper right
这个标签是在右上角的位置
of our screen and is drawn to the right
并且从右上角的右侧从左往右
from the left.
绘制标签文字
So the label draws off the screen.
所以这个文本被画在了屏幕外面
Change the anchor and alignment properties
把锚定和调整属性改为
to upper right
右上
and right.
右
We can see our Restart Text label
这下我们看到Restart Text的文本标签
now draws to the left from the right
在右上角
starting in the upper right corner.
已经从右往左绘制了
The second adjustment is to the pixel offset.
第二处需要变更的地方就是像素偏移
Let's match the pixel offset
让我们把Restart Text像素偏移
on Restart Text to that of Score Text.
设置成与Score Text(得分文本)匹配的格式
We can have the same 10 pixel pad
我们选择10个像素的空间
by setting the pixel offset to
这就是说像素偏移的值设定为
-10 and -10.
-10 和 -10
Add Restart Text to DisplayText
把Restart Text这个文本对象也拖拽到
to keep our Hierarchy neat and tidy.
DisplayText里保持我们的层级结构整齐干净
Create another GUI text object.
再新建一个GUI text对象
And rename this one Game Over Text.
重命名为Game Over文本
Change the text property to Game Over Text.
把文本的属性改为Game Over Text
Change the anchor and alignment to
把锚定和调整
middle centre
改为中部中心
and centre.
和中心
And change the transform's position Y
将transform的position的Y属性设置为
to 0.6
0.6
so it is in the middle of our screen but up a bit.
这样它就在屏幕的中心稍微靠上一点
Now add Game Over Text
现在再把Game Over Text文本
to our Display Text parent game object.
拖拽到我们的Display Text父类中
This sets up the basic GUI text objects
这下所有需要用来结束游戏的
that we will need to end our game.
文本都已经准备好了
Next we need to update our code
下一步我们需要更新我们
on our GameController script.
GameController脚本中的代码
Open our GameController script for editing.
打开GameController脚本并编辑
We need to create references to our new
我们需要新建一些对刚才建好的文本
GUI text components.
的引用
Write public GUIText restartText
敲入代码public GUIText restartText
and public GUIText gameOverText.
和public GUIText gameOverText
We will feed information to these labels
我们将随着游戏的进行把相应信息
as the game progresses.
反馈给这些文本标签
To control what we sent to these 2 labels
为了控制何时发送和
and when we send it we will need
发送什么给这些文本标签
2 related control flags,
我们需要两个相关的控制标志
or 2 boolean variables.
或者说是2个布尔变量
Let's write private bool for boolean gameOver
让我们敲入private bool gameOver
and private bool restart.
private bool restart作为控制标志
These true-false boolean flags will help
这些只表示真假的布尔标志
us track when the game is over and
将帮助我们追踪游戏何时结束
when it is okay to restart the game.
和游戏什么时候可以再开始
We need to set the value for these at the
我们需要在游戏开始的时候将
start of the game.
这些标志初始化
So in Start write
所以在Start函数中敲入
gameOver = false and restart = false.
gameOver = false 和 restart = false.
We also need to set the starting text
我们还需要在我们新文本标签中
on our new labels so let's write
设置开始的文本内容
restartText.text = ""
敲入restartText.text = ""
The same for gameOverText.text.
gameOverText.text也这么写
Set this to 2 empty quotes as well.
内容也是一对双引号内容是空
This means at the start of the game
这意味着在游戏开始的时候
these 2 GUI text labels
这2个GUI text标签的文本
will display nothing.
什么也不会显示
These labels are effectively turned off.
这些标签从功能上说是被关掉的
We need to change the state of our game
我们需要在游戏结束的时候
and the content of these labels when
更改游戏的状态
our game is over.
并且变更文本标签的内容
Much like adding our score we need
就像我们击毁小行星得分那样
to expose a function here
这里我们也需要写一个函数
on our game controller for another object
这个写在controller中的函数
to call when the game is over.
会在游戏结束时被其他对象调用
Let's create a new public function we can
让我们新建可以从当前脚本外调用的
call from outside this script.
公有的函数
Write public void GameOver.
敲入public void GameOver
Our function will need no parameters.
这个函数不需要形参
It simply gets called to end the game.
它只是在游戏结束的时候被调用
Our GameOver function is very simple.
我们的GameOver 函数很简单
First we set our gameOverText.text to
首先设定gameOverText.text的内容为
Game Over!
And then we set our GameOver flag to true.
然后设定GameOver的标志变成真
Now we will use our Game Over flag
现在我们要用这个Game Over标志
to break out of the infinite loop
来中断我们
that spawns our hazards.
生成小行星的无限循环
The spawn loop is a while loop.
这个生成小行星的循环是一个while循环
The while loop will continue cycling
这个while循环会不停的
through the code it holds until the
循环执行它包含的代码直到
statement in the parenthesis is false.
参数的状态变为假
We have set this literally to true
这里我们当时直接设置成了真
so without help this loop will never end.
因此如果没别的影响这个循环永远都不会结束
At the end of the loop, after we have waited
在这个循环的末尾等待一波小行星
for our wave to clear, but before we loop back
被清理干净但还没开始下一个
to the top of our block of code
循环的位置我们添加新代码
add if gameOver.
敲入if(gameOver)
And when written this way we are saying the
当我们这么写的时候
same thing as if gameOver is
它语法的意义与判断
the same as true
gameOver是否是真相同
restartText.text equals
敲入restartText.text =
Press R for restart.
"Press 'R' for restart"
And again, within a string of text
再强调一下
enclosed by double quotes
双引号内的字符串文本
note that the R is enclosed by single quotes.
中R两侧使用的是单引号
This sets our restart label.
这些设定了我们重新开始标签的内容
Next set our restart boolean flag to true.
下一步把重新开始的布尔标签设置成真
And lastly write break.
最后写下break
This will break us out of our while loop.
这个代码会中断我们的while循环
And as there is no more code to execute
因为spawnWaves在这之后
in spawnWaves after the break
没有需要执行的代码了
it will end the spawnWaves coroutine.
那么这个spawnWaves 协程就会被结束
In our Restart Text label
在我们的重新开始文本标签中
we have informed our player that they
我们已经告知了玩家
can restart the game by pressing
他们可以通过按R键
the R key.
重新开始游戏
We will now write the code that allows
我们现在要写代码
the player to do this.
允许玩家重新开始游戏
To easily capture a key press
为了更简单的捕捉按键
let's poll for it in update.
让我们在update插入代码
Write void update
敲入void update
and in the update function write
在update函数中写下
if restart
if(restart)
so if restart is true we look for our
所以如果restart为真我们就查看
key press with if Input.GetKeyDown KeyCode.R
按键的情况代码是if(Input.GetKeyDown KeyCode.R)
Now if restart is true and we get
如果restart的标志是真
the key press on the R key
同时R键也被按下了
we reload this scene by using
我们就把这个场景重新加载
Application.LoadLevel.
代码是Application.LoadLevel
Application.LoadLevel loads the level
Application.LoadLevel会重新载入
or scene file specified in the parenthesis.
参数标明的场景
Instead of writing a string name
我们这里直接填入
or using an index number for that scene
Application.LoadedLevel来重新载入
we will simply use the currently loaded level
当前场景而不使用索引数字
by using Application.LoadedLevel
或者一个字符串名字
That's it for this script.
这个脚本差不多完成了
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
We need to set up our new references
我们需要把刚编辑的GameController
that we have written on GameController.
中的引用配置一下
With GameController selected
选定GameController
drag the RestartText game object
把RestartText对象
on to the Restart Text slot
拖拽到GameController组件的
on the GameController component.
Restart Text槽
Next drag the GameOver text
然后把GameOver text对象
game object on to the Game Over text
也拖拽到GameController组件的
slot on the GameController component.
Game Over槽
We are now done with our game controller.
现在我们的游戏控制器完成了
To end the game we need to call Game Over
为了结束游戏我们需要完成
on Game Controller when the player
当玩家被击毁后对Game Over
is destroyed.
的调用
We could try to detect this on the
我们可以在玩家对象上
player game object,
做这个检测
but we have already written this code somewhere else.
但是这个功能代码其实已经在其他地方写过了
Our AsteroidHazards already detect
我们的小行星检测过
collisions with our player.
它与玩家的碰撞
and that collision destroys the player game object.
这个碰撞会销毁玩家飞船
Open the DestroyByContact script for editing.
打开DestroyByContact 脚本并编辑
In our DestroyByContact code
在DestroyByContact的代码中
we detect if other.tag is the same as Player.
我们检测other.tag是否为Player
Then before we destroy the player game object
在我们销毁玩家对象之前
we instantiate the player explosion.
我们实例化了玩家对象的爆炸
After the line where we spawn the player
在生成玩家爆炸的代码后面
explosion write gameController,
写下代码gameController
which is the variable holding the reference
这个参数保存了对
to our game controller instance,
gameController实例的引用
and with the dot call the GameOver function
然后使用点语法我们调用了
on GameController.
GameController的GameOver函数
Now when we destroy the player game object
现在当玩家飞船被击毁的时候
our game controller is told that the
我们的游戏控制器会被告知
game is over.
游戏已经结束了
Save this script and return to Unity.
保存脚本回到Unity
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
保存场景进入游戏模式
When the player is destroyed we see the
当玩家飞船被击毁
Game Over label.
我们可以看到游戏结束的文本标签
When the current wave clears the screen
当目前屏幕上的小行星被清除后
we can restart by pressing the R key.
我们可以按R键重新开始游戏
And we're playing again.
我们可以再玩一次
Note that the game doesn't instantly restart.
注意一下游戏不是马上重新开始的
Nor can we restart the level for a few moments
我们得等一会游戏才能重新开始
while we wait for the screen to clear.
我们等待屏幕被上的小行星飞出屏幕
This gives the player a clear sense that
这样就可以给玩家一个明显的感觉
the game is over before restarting the level.
游戏已经结束我们可以重新开始
Make sure that we have exited Play mode.
先退出游戏模式
The last step in this assignment is to add
本章节的最后一个步骤是
a little more style to our GUI text labels.
给我们的文本增加一些样式
We will be using multi-object editing.
我们会使用到多对象编辑
Select both Restart Text and Score Text.
选择Restart Text和Score Text文本
These are the labels in the upper corners
这些都是屏幕上方角落的文本
and change their font size to 20.
把他们的字体大小调整到20
Next select the Game Over text
然后选择Game Over文本
and set it's font size to 25.
把它的字体大小设置为25
This will make these labels easier to read.
这样这些标签就更看着就更舒服了
Save the scene and enter Play mode.
保存场景进入游戏模式
Fantastic.
很棒
Our game is complete.
我们的游戏已经完成
In the last assignment we will build the
在最后的章节中
game as a web player and deploy it
我们会把这个游戏作为网页游戏生成
to the web to play.
然后把他们发布到网页上